This is a snapshot of Dutch soccer fans
doing what Dutch soccer fans do best.
For decades, following their national
team, the traveling fans have dawned
their orange, assembled by the
thousands, and walked city streets
behind the famed orange bus to the
hosting stadium. And June 20th, 2026 was
no different. Taking public transit and
biking to meet a university campus at
the edge of the host city's museum
district, an estimated 25,000 fans
headed south. Following a residential
avenue, the massive crowd benefited from
the shade of an urban canopy of old
growth oaks lining the roadway.
Daylighting onto Main Street, they then
crossed a waterway bordered by a
pedestrian trail. Now nearing the
stadium, the crowd merged alongside the
path of the city's light rail. Following
the red line southbound, they arrived at
the city's stadium center. across three
miles or 5 kilometers through wooded,
fairly compact neighborhoods, crossing
canals and pedestrian trails, bordering
along a mass transit [music] system, the
route would feel a fairly standard one
for the traveling Dutch fans, aside from
perhaps the heat. Because while the
route doesn't seem so out of the
ordinary for the walking European
superfan, this is Houston, Texas, which
even within a state known for being car
obsessed, within a country known for
being car obsessed, is known by
Americans to be unwalkable, sprawling,
and carob obsessed. What this 3M World
Cup jaunt serves to show is that
Houston, along with its home state, are
easy to stereotype and oversimplify, but
on the ground level, they're beginning
to look a little different.
Texas is of course booming, but the
U-Haul growth index, which simply looks
at the destination of oneway trucks
rented, Texas has been either the number
one or number two most common
destination for movers every year since
2016. And by the ever so cliche
indicator that's usually saved for
California, if Texas were its own
country, it'd be the world's eighth
largest by GDP. And you, of course, know
all this. Elon Musk talks about it. Greg
Abbott brags about it. Fox News
showcases it. And the state itself
revels in it. But this Texas-sized
population boom and corresponding
economic miracle is more complicated
than two sides of a highly politicized
representation. While the bedrock has
always been energy and gas exports, it's
more than good old boys racking up
absurd wealth on fossil fuels, as the
left would leave you thinking. And while
business relocation and local investment
has pushed the state economy to grow to
pace faster than most others, it's more
than just a lack of red tape and
conservative values opening up
opportunities. As the boosters from the
right would have you to believe, both
energy and a comparatively pro business
environment are major contributors. But
Texas has been growing upward for so
long because of something more basic.
It's just a remarkably steady growth
engine that hasn't shown any real signs
of slowing until perhaps now. Steadily
growing without really slowing is a
simple concept, but in a world of finite
resources, it's a uniquely challenging
cycle to simulate and maintain. And to
understand how Texas just grows and
grows, we need to consider where Texas
[music] grows. This is the Texas
triangle. It's along the three points of
this triangle, the Houston area, the
Dallas Fort Worth metro area, and the
Austin and San Antonio metro area, where
you find the highest population
densities within the state. And it's
along these urban areas' outskirts where
you find the fastest growing population
centers within the fastest growing
state. In line with population
concentration, this triangle makes up
for 70% of the state's total population
is relative economic might as the
triangle generates almost 80% of the
state's GDP. And all of this is driven
by the points on the triangle. Take
Houston. In the 1830s, Texas struck out
as its own country. It wanted its
independence from Mexico, but it wanted
to be a slaveolding state annexed
[music] into the US during a period
where annexing a slaveolding state was a
tough political cell. So, it set off on
its own and it put its capital right
here for the first couple years in
Houston, where the Rice, now a
residential building, stands. While the
independence of the Republic of Texas
wouldn't last long, a statewide sense of
independence would. [music] In 1948, a
century after the state had joined the
union, Houston voters bucked the trend
sweeping across most major cities in the
US and voted against adopting a
city-wide zoning ordinance or a
municipal law that would outline what
type of buildings would be built where.
In the next decade, the city doubled in
size and nearly [music] reached a
million inhabitants. And as it crossed
the million member mark in the early
1960s, residents again voted against
zoning ordinances. This legacy has led
to things like this Huckleberry Circle
where expensive single family homes are
abudded by massive apartment towers. It
also made room for things like
never-ending parking lots and this
picture in particular. From the '7s,
this shot has become synonymous with
Houston's car obsession and lack of
central vision in creating a cityscape.
This is the heart of the city, just
blocks away from where the Republic of
Texas Capital Building once stood. But
again, it's an oversimplification to
call Houston an unwockable, unplanned
[music] urban disaster. For one, this
same area of downtown has fundamentally
transformed over the last 50 years. It
now looks like this. But more
importantly, and more transformatively,
this unique lack of zoning on account of
just not wanting ordinances
unintentionally opened a lane for the
city to become an unrelenting growth
machine. With limited rules outside of
lot minimums in mid-century Houston, the
energy sector boomed and the city
sprawled to a size larger than the
entire London metro area. A big city
built for cars and car parking with
continued demand for more housing then
started to change on account of
opportunistic land developers and
builders.
Since the 1990s, Houston has been
infilling housing and it has created a
virtuous cycle. Take for example this
lot in northwest Houston. Located in a
quiet residential neighborhood called
Acre Homes. This traditionally would be
a lot for a single family home set a
good bit off the streets, perhaps just
like its neighbor across the alleyway.
But instead, a local design and planning
firm had a different idea for the lot.
Rather than one lot, they've split it
into four. Rather than a single family
home, it's now slated to serve
potentially four families. At least in
theory, this creates benefits for both
developers and residents. CGE planning
rather than building and selling one
larger home for say $400,000 can now
build out and sell four homes for
$150,000 each and make 50% more on
sales. And while turning a profit, they
can also be proud of their community
impact. They're providing four homes to
be sold at a comparatively low price.
That through increasing the neighborhood
population density, helps local
business, incentivizes further business
development, makes the neighborhood more
dynamic and appealing to more
pro-density development, which makes the
area more walkable, more welcoming, more
livable. And it's not just a theory.
It's already happening here. Just look
down the street. All these homes are on
small footprints, and they're all cheap.
This phenomena is most acutely felt here
within the I610 motorway, which rims the
core of the city. In the [music] '90s,
applications to replplat big lots to
smaller lots had become so common that
city officials didn't want to deal with
them on a case-by case basis. So, they
dropped minimum lot size from 5,000 ft
to,400 ft and reduced mandatory setbacks
of homes from 25 ft to just 5 ft off the
street. Within this loop, denser and
denser housing has allowed the area to
maintain about 4,500 people living
within each square mile. Nothing crazy
in terms of density, but on par with the
likes of Sacramento, Long Beach, and
Atlanta. Surprisingly, given the city's
reputation, it's becoming more and more
bikable, while the Interloop has a
fairly high walkability score. But an
uptick in population density and better
walkability scores don't speak to why
Houston has been such a draw in the last
25 years. It's the fact that these
denser housing projects are cheap, too.
Of the 20 largest metro areas in the US,
Houston has the second cheapest housing,
backing its welcoming reputation with
real economic opportunity for new
arrivals. Depending on rankings, Houston
is the US's most diverse or second most
diverse major city. Houston is
welcoming, and this is partly due to the
city's heritage. This was once Mexico.
This is also a historically black city
and serves as one of the best landing
spots for black professionals with
nearly a fifth of all businesses
blackowned and a professional workforce
where about 20% of teachers and 20% of
doctors are black. It's been a welcoming
city to refugees whether that's
Vietnamese relocating during the 1970s
or the quarter of a million that were
displaced during Hurricane Katrina. And
it's also structurally welcoming thanks
to infill. Houston adds housing and
people without seeing its housing prices
shoot skyward. Because housing and cost
of living is relatively cheap, it's a
place where construction jobs, food and
service jobs, manufacturing jobs can
more than make ends meet. Houston is by
no means perfect. It's fairly segregated
in places. Gentrification is pushing out
families in other areas like the third
ward. But on the whole, it's a leader in
opportunities for minorities. Infill is
also being matched by overflow as the
Houston suburbs continue to grow, too.
And it's the same thing because there's
so much room to grow. There's high
demand, but the supply isn't strained,
so it stays cheap. Because the building
sector keeps humming, the growth machine
keeps running no matter how hot the
summers get. Or apparently how cold the
winters get. 3 and 1/2 hours up
Interstate 45 from Houston is Dallas, or
really Dallas, Fort Worth, Arlington,
and a host of suburbs from Plano to
Irving that are putting Houston's growth
numbers to shame. The metro area has
even passed Houston in recent years as
the fourth most populous in the US. And
as far as places for cities to sit, this
place isn't the best. The de facto
capital of North Texas, the Dallas Fort
Worth area is a southern plain city. And
as such, it's prone to get hit by the
occasional ice storm during the winter
and we'll see the occasional snowstorm
or two. Once summer hits though, it's
relentlessly hot and muggy, stacking
streaks of 100° Fahrenheit or 38° C days
for weeks on end. And between those two
extremes, when hot happens to run into
cold, there are tornadoes with one
having actually touched down in downtown
Fort Worth in 2000. The weather just
isn't great. And as for navigable
waterways around here, practically a
necessity for any major American city,
well, there aren't any of those either.
Not that they didn't try. While Houston
benefits from the navigable Buffalo
Bayou, Port Houston, and buoyancy to
help float its economy, Dallas [music]
has no such advantage. They just have
the Trinity River. Early city boosters
believed that with a little engineering,
the Trinity could connect North Texas to
the Gulf, and for a few decades, the
Army Corps of Engineers tried, but to no
avail. But Dallas, as it is now, was
nothing if not determined. It became a
rail hub. It became a cattle hub, and
the area is now a natural gas hub. Sheer
will and boosterism from city founders
put Dallas on the map. With little in
the way of physical advantages, the city
has brought in big business by building
a big airport, keeping operational costs
low, and maintaining a large, skilled,
comparatively cheap workforce through
breakneck home building. And now the
area has over 20 Fortune 500 companies
to show for it, only trailing New York
City and Chicago. With Texas
Instruments, Toyota North America,
Charles Schwab, Kameri, AT&T, and
Caterpillar, the area has become a hub
for everything from tech and finance to
heavy machinery. More companies are
coming, and more people are, too. Now
that it's on the map, the city, as much
as anywhere in the state, has leaned
into its natural geographic advantage.
There's just a lot of flat land around
here. Less glitzy, less nationally
prominent, less populous and sizable
than Dallas is Fort Worth. While
downtown Dallas is corporate, Fort Worth
has the stockyards. While Dallas feels
metropolitan with a Texas flare, Fort
Worth just feels like Texas. But long in
Dallas's shadow, Fort Worth is now
stealing headlines. It recently passed
Austin in population, it ranks high
among the nation's fastest growing
cities, and it's on Dallas's heels. The
city is growing fast and really not
showing signs of slowing because of how
it's growing. Conceived in the
mid-century, then built out in the 80s,
the I820 loop was meant to be a beltway
that surrounded Fort Worth and connected
the city's suburbs. But now, the city
limits look like this. Fort Worth spills
out in just about every direction beyond
the confines of the beltway. Fort Worth
is able to add population as fast as
anywhere in the state because it's
adding land just about as fast as
anywhere in the state. Fort Worth is
annexing its suburbs and adding single
family developments to keep up with the
demands for more housing in the region.
The Terraella development is under
construction right now, but you can buy
a five- bedroomedroom house for under
$400,000.
Just about anywhere else, that's a
steal, and this one comes with a Fort
Worth address, meaning you'd be living
large in one of America's biggest
[music] and fastest growing cities. But
this development happens to be here, 20
mi out from downtown. And while it's
just a construction site now, it's
planned to be the most generic of single
family suburban developments. And yet,
somehow it's now Fort Worth. While
providing utilities, municipal services
like police and fire will fall on the
city. It's a worthwhile trade-off
because it adds to the tax base in an
important way through property tax while
also adding to city housing stock to at
least help keep up with demand. Because
Fort Worth has been an especially
popular destination since co rents and
housing prices have gone upward, but by
national averages, they're still low
[music] and they're still lower than
Dallas is which speaks to another facet
as to why Fort Worth is reaching farther
north. They're following the firms,
companies, and major employers that are
moving out of Dallas and up into the
northern suburbs. AT&T, Fifth Third
Bank, Neiman Marcus, even the
professional sports franchises, [music]
the Dallas Stars, and Dallas Mavericks
have left or are planning to leave
downtown Dallas for perhaps not greener,
but cheaper pastures north. Dallas is
cheap by national standards. Fort Worth
is cheap by Dallas standards. But these
counties in the suburbs are cheap by
North Texas [music] standards, and it's
proving a major draw. Access to the city
at suburb prices has counties
surrounding the Dallas Fort Worth metro
area growing by more than 30% in a
decade. Its cheap square footage, new
houses that go up fast, quaint smaller
suburban downtowns with fairly
accessible big cities nearby that have
places like Frisco, Plano, and Irving
booming. Former Californians tickled by
the price tags and lack of taxes and
former Midwesterners working remote and
searching for a change are now chasing
the Texas dream, while North Texas is
doing everything it can to keep up and
maintain the validity of such a dream.
Where Houston has infill, North Texas
has fully embraced the sprawl. And with
planes and planes to spread across, it
too seems like an engine for stubbornly
steady growth. But eventually, at some
point, inevitably, unavoidably, there
reaches a limit to the Texas dream, and
Austin, Texas may be [music] ground
zero. This was the original growth
machine. Tesla, Oracle, Apple, all set
up here. Elon Musk, Joe Rogan, and
basically anyone that was fed up with CO
policies, coastal red tape restricting
business, or just the plain sky-high
cost of living in Chicago, LA, the Bay
Area, or New York seemed to be taking
their money and their business to
Austin. In migration had the city
growing at a 4% clip from 2010 to 2020.
Since then, it slowed to about a single
percent a year. Middle- inome earners
have stagnated. Low-income earners are
leaving as the city has gone from a
weird, sleepy university town to an
increasingly hip tech hub. Picking up
the slack, perhaps creating the slack,
too, are Dripping Springs, Round Rock,
and Liberty Hill. The suburbs where
again, the city isn't too far, the job
is nearby or within a short commute.
[music] And the dollar goes a little bit
farther than it would in Austin. What
Austin has learned, and what Dallas is
quickly learning, is that the Texas
dream is a mobile one. The Texas
triangle, the growth machine that fuels
and is fueled by the dream of an easy
commute, a cheap house, a friendly
business environment, and a hopping
economy, is changing in shape. It's
pushing north out of Dallas. It's
pushing into the suburbs of Houston and
Austin. It's filling in between the
cities. For the state, this broadly
works. For the new arrival, this broadly
works. But it's putting cities in a bit
of a bind. Any longtime Austinite will
tell you that Austin has changed. A city
that loved the keep Austin weird
stickers is just no longer that weird.
It's less steampunk and more Silicon
Valley than ever. That may seem a
privileged problem or one of taste
rather than substance, but there are
real ramifications. In a state that
taxes pretty lightly, these cities
really count on property taxes. And with
things cooling, Austin is now facing
backtoback years of a shrinking tax
role. Recently, on account of low sales
tax revenue, Dallas announced it would
be furlowing some city employees as its
sales tax growth is lagging behind those
in Plano, [music] Frisco, and Irving. If
the Texas dream is a mobile one, it may
prove to be a brush fire, burning fast
across the planes, following easy fuel,
and leaving burn scars behind. But, as
it seems every Texas booster would want
you to believe, that all may be a
problem for tomorrow.
When I started researching Texas for
this video, I was reminded how difficult
it is to understand a place this large
and influential. It's not just that
Texas is complicated. It's that almost
every discussion about it comes with a
different interpretation of what's
actually happening. That's one of the
challenges of making videos like this.
The research is expansive, but the final
explanation has to be concise, which
means constantly deciding which details
are essential and which are simply
interesting. That's one of the reasons
I've kept using Ground News while
researching videos like this since I
first partnered with them in 2023. Their
app and website helps me compare
coverage across hundreds of outlets, see
where the reporting converges or
differs, and build a more complete
picture before drawing my own
conclusions. Just take, for example, the
coverage of a fatal shooting in Houston
by an ICE agent. Ground News shows me
that over 400 outlets covered this
story. Scrolling through, I can quickly
see the political distribution of
coverage, how factual the reporting has
historically been, who owns the outlets,
and even filter by location to compare
local coverage to international
reporting. The left focuses on the use
of deadly force, while the right focuses
on who the victim was and the alleged
circumstances that preceded it. Both
headlines describe the same event, but
they lead readers towards very different
interpretations. That's why I don't rely
on a single outlet or an algorithm that
keeps serving me more of the same.
[music] Comparing coverage helps
separate the underlying facts from the
framing, but that's only part of the
picture. Just as important are the
stories that never reach your radar in
the first place. Ground News's blind
spot feed surfaces stories receiving
significant attention from one side of
the political spectrum, but
comparatively little from the other. The
goal isn't to consume more news, it's to
understand [music] it better. That's why
I've kept using ground news for years.
It doesn't tell me what to think. It
gives me the context to reach my own
conclusions. It's also independently run
and subscriber funded. To help you get
the most of it, I partner with Ground
News to offer you guys 40% off the same
unlimited access advantage plan I use at
ground.new/wendover
or by scanning the QR code on screen.